Register of the Charles Hill Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Stanford Years File, 1989-1992. (Box 31)
  - Speeches and writings (Box 35)
    - 1990
      - Middle East, October 1
      - "Soviet Union,", October 8
      - "Constructive Reflections on the Budget Debacle,", October 15
      - "Iraq and Kuwait: The U.S. Involvement," Institute for Historical Study Round Table, October 17.
      - "Statecraft for the Future,", November 2
      - "Middle East: The Post Cold War Order Begins," program, November 6
      - "Tales of the United Nations,", November 9
    - 1991
      - "Why the U.S. Policy in the Gulf Is Right,", January 23
      - "An Arms Control Initiative for the Middle East,", February 26
      - "Let's Get Our Middle East Act Together,", March 29
      - Notes, Conference on Central Europe, May 9
      - Statement on Rajiv Gandhi's assassination, May 21
      - "Mongolia and Latvia,", May 22
      - Report on the Middle East, Hoover Overseers, July 27
      - "Experts Discuss Chances for an Uprising," San Francisco Chronicle, August 20
      - "Action International,", August 25
      - "A Contrapuntal Civilization," Stanford Convocation, September 27
      - Letter to the editor on Vietnam, SHAFR Newsletter, September
      - Notes on the Middle East, November 19
  - Subject file (Box 37)
    - Adams, John Quincy.
      Printed matter
    - Anderson, Martin. Letter from John Carlson, 1990, regarding presentation at Hoover Institution
    - Bacon, Francis. "Chief Guides for the Study of Bacon's Speeches"
    - Barden, Alison M. Correspondence, campaign materials
    - Bozeman, Adda.
      Correspondence with Anne van Camp, Hoover Institution; autobiographical sketch
    - Bunka-viewing by Meredith Palmer
    - Cambodia. Charles Hill notes
    - Catholic Church
      - General, including New York Times article on Our Lady of Fatima, May 14, 1991
      - Capitalism. "Centesimus Annus," Papal encyclical, May 2, 1991
        printed matter
      - Catholic Universities - Apostolic Constitution.
      - Liberation theology. Papal Instructions, 1984, 1986, 1990
    - Chamberlain, George Agnew (writer, friend of Amelia Earhart).
    - Chogyam Trungpa.
      See Rinpoche
    - Cyprus. Map and travel advisory
    - Dean, John - Memo from George Vest to Charles Hill
    - Egyptian stories. Chronology
    - El Salvador. Letter from Ward Beecher to George Shultz on the release of Beecher's daughter from detention in El Salvador, December 1, 1989
    - Freud, Sigmund. Quote in letter to Wilhelm Fliess on bisexuality, August 1, 1899
    - Germany and German unification. Bibliography
    - Herzog, Chaim. Introduction and guest list
    - Hook, Sidney.
      See Hoover Institution
    - Hoover Institution
      - Hook, Sidney. Suggestions for position formerly held by Sidney Hook
      - Hoover Fund for Institution Building in Central Europe, May 2, 1990
      - Hoover Press
      - Young Diplomats Program
    - Institute of International Studies, Stanford University
    - Institute of Nautical Archaeology.
    - Iraq/Kuwait
      - Charles Hill notes
      - Synopsis of talk by Lt. Cols. Sullivan and Townson, "Military Options in the Persian Gulf,", November 1, 1990
      - Chronology
      - Paper on U.S. objectives, February 1991
      - Speeches by William Stanton, January 9 and March 1991
      - Proceedings of Washington Institute, September 14-16, 1990; research memo, October 1990
      - Printed matter, 1982, 1990-1991
    - Israel-Lebanon. Agreement on withdrawal of troops from Lebanon, May 17, 1983
    - James, Henry. Quote from Hawthorne on what American life lacked when compared with the European, 1879 (Box 38)
    - Jasper Ridge. "History of Jasper Ridge"
    - Jordan. Charles Hill's draft of a letter to King Hussein, May 1989
    - Kuwait. Materials from the Free Kuwait Action Committee, 1991
    - Liberation theology.
    - Love and Marriage. Colloquium given by Susan Treggiari, July 18, 1990
    - MacNeil/Lehrer Newshour. Letter to George Shultz from Linda Winslow regarding the Statecraft Project, May 1990
    - Agreement., May 17, 1983
      See Israel-Lebanon Agreement
    - McCarran-Walter Act.
    - Middle East. Written interview with Rachel Sneh on the cease-fire agreement between Israel and the Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO), July 1981
    - Miscellany
    - National Defense University Press. Bibliography
    - Nixon, Richard. Activities in 1985
    - Psomas, Andreas - Papers
    - Rain forests. "Political and Economic Causes for the Destruction of Tropical Rain Forests and Some Suggested Solutions" by Bonnie Gorsic, December 8, 1989
    - Shultz, George
      - Correspondence
        - Brundtland, Gro Harlem, 1989
        - Kennedy, Donald, 1989
      - Remarks by Max Kampelman honoring George Shultz before the Anti-Defamation League, June 14, 1989
      - Speeches and writings
        - "U.S. Foreign Policy: Realism and Progress"
        - "National Policies and Global Prosperity,", April 11, 1985
        - "Public Service in America,", January 9, 1989
        - Remarks, January 19, 1989
    - Sports. Poetry
    - Stanford University
      - Center for International Security and Arms Control. Arms control course, March 1990
      - Donald Kennedy memo to George Shultz, "Global Stanford,", June 1989
      - Medical Center, October 1990
    - Students for East European Democracy (S.E.E.D.)
    - "Taba Project," Myron Gubitz
    - Ugaritic literature. Outline
    - United States. Department of State
      - General
        - Performance evaluations
        - Phone numbers
        - Reply to letter of inquiry
      - Foreign policy. "A New U.S. Strategic Concept" by Paul Nitze
      - Foreign Service. Printed matter, October 1989
    - Vatican.
    - Vietnam. Department of State Library booklist
    - World Affairs Report. Letter from Ronald Hilton, May 1989
- Closed Materials (Box 39-51)
- Increment received in 1992 (Box 52)
  Biographical files, career files, correspondence, speeches and writings (including Statecraft project and projects with George Shultz), subject file, Department of State file, Stanford Years files, Political Officer in Hong Kong file, United Nations file, and audio-visual files, listed as increments were received
  - Biographical file
    - General
    - Hill, Martha
    - Media appearances
    - Miscellany
    - Travel
  - Career file
  - Correspondence, 1989-1992 (Box 52-53)
    - General
    - Abrams, Elliott, 1990 (Box 54)
    - American Express, 1989-1990
    - Armacost, Michael, 1989
    - Barnes, Harry, Jr., 1989-1992
    - Bell, Muriel, 1989-1990
    - Boeker, Paul, 1989
    - Brinker, William, 1991
    - Brookins, Carol, 1989
    - Crocker, Chester, 1992
    - Doherty, William, 1991-1992
    - Eagleburger, Lawrence, 1989-1992
    - Glassboro State College, 1989-1992
    - Griswold, Charles, 1989-1990
    - Hill, Emily, 1992
    - Hill, Katie, undated
    - Institute for International Studies, Stanford University, 1990-1991
    - International Center for Development Policy, 1990
    - Kagan, Robert, 1991-1992
    - LaFeber, Walter, 1989-1990
    - Nader, George, 1989-1992
  - Speeches and writings (Box 55)
    - "An Agenda for Peace," United Nations
    - Arms Control Initiative
    - "Arms Control, the Middle East and the Next International System"
    - "Beyond Containment: The M Factor"
    - "Can the Middle East Keep Up?"
    - Remarks, Chatham House, London
    - "Diplomacy of the Arab-Israeli Conflict: The 'Peace Process', 1967-1991"
    - "Diplomacy and Terrorism"
    - "Foreign Policy Making in the Reagan Administration"
    - Interview on the Gulf War, 1991.
      Radio, KZSU
    - Interview with George Shultz and tribute to Philip Habib's memory
    - Remarks on Honduras
    - Outline on Statecraft and Diplomacy project, Hoover Institution
    - "Hotel and the Mosque: The Middle East in the World Economy"
    - "How Should We Think About Foreign Policy?"
    - "Imperative of Realism in the Middle East"
    - "Let's Get Our Middle East Act Together"
    - "Middle East 'Peace Process'...a Story of Contending Concepts"
    - Miscellany
    - "Neglected Dimension of the Middle East Conflict"
    - Negotiation
    - "New Departures for the Nation-State" (Box 56)
    - "On Governance"
    - "On Language Learning"
    - "A Pocket History of the 'Peace Process' in the Middle East"
    - "Reflections on Drug Policy"
    - "Restatement of American Democracy"
    - Remarks, Stanford World Institute
    - "Summit Fatigue"
    - "Tales of the United Nations"
    - "Twelve Months of the Middle East"
    - United Nations. Remarks of Boutros Boutros-Ghali, Royal Institute of International Affairs
    - "Vietnam"
    - "What Qualities Enabled the Romans to Become Masters of the Mediterranean World?"
    - "White Whales and Dead White Males"
    - Statecraft project (Box 57)
      - General
        - Bibliography
        - Book proposal
        - Logic chain
        - Project proposal
        - Quotations
        - Research materials
        - Table of contents
      - Edited draft of book
      - Book draft (Box 58)
        - Introduction
        - Chapter 1 - Statecraft
        - Chapter 2 - Civilization
        - Chapter 3 - Diplomacy
        - Chapter 4 - The Next New Age
        - Chapter 5 - The Proving Ground of Ideas - Democracy
        - Chapter 6 - War
        - Chapter 7 - Future War
        - Chapter 8 - The New Wealth of Nations
        - Chapter 9 - The Planet
        - Chapter 10 - The Public Eye
        - Chapter 11 - Sovereignty and Nations
        - Chapter 12 - Withdrawal and Return
      - Miscellaneous drafts (Box 59)
      - Television series
        - Interview with Jim Lehrer of the MacNeil/Lehrer Newshour, and George Shultz, 1989
        - Possible format for television series
        - Television series outlines and plans (Box 60)
      - A Statecraft for the Future - draft and typed copy
    - Projects with George Shultz
      - Secretary of State Library (3 computer disks)
      - Turmoil and Triumph: My Years as Secretary of State, 1993
        - Introduction
        - Parts I-IV
        - Bibliography
        - Drafts/research materials
        - Draft A (Box 61)
          - Andropov, Yuri
          - Berezhkov, Andrei
          - Bitburg
          - Boland amendments
          - Cambodia
          - Can Ronald Reagan Be Explained?
          - Central America (back-up)
          - Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) and the Contras
          - Chile
          - China
          - Cold War Is Over
          - Coming of Age in the Nuclear Age
          - Continuing Search for Peace in the Middle East
          - Daniloff, Nicholas
          - Day After
          - Eastern Europe
          - Great Britain
          - Gromyko, Andrei
          - Hostages (Box 62)
          - Interlock: the Shultz Initiative
          - Iran/Contra
          - Iraq and Iran
          - Japan
          - Last of the Superpower Summits
          - Lebanon
          - Libya
          - Middle East Peace Process
          - Miscellany, including some reader comments
          - Noriega, Manuel (Box 63)
          - Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO)
          - Philippines
          - Pipeline
          - Polecat
          - Press/media
          - Reagan, Nancy
          - Reagan Doctrine
          - Reflections, including folder labeled "Material not used yet, (in May 19, 1992 draft)"
          - Representation: A Lesson From My Time With President Nixon
          - Reykjavik
          - Sea Change (Box 64)
            - Central America
            - Korea
            - Middle East
            - Reflagging
          - Southern Africa
          - Soviet Union
          - Terrorism
          - Things Fall Apart (Box 65)
          - Tiresome, Troublesome, and Trivial
          - Transition
          - Turning Points
          - World Turmoil
          - Wounded White House: Iran-Contra
        - Draft B
          - Introduction
          - Afghanistan: The End of the Brezhnev Doctrine
          - Brunei
          - Can Ronald Reagan Be Explained?
          - Central America
          - CIA and the Contras: New Concerns, 1986
          - Daniloff
          - End of Colonialism in Africa
          - Fall of Marcos
          - Interlock: The Shultz Initiative, 1988
          - Iran-Contra: Picking Up the Pieces, 1987
          - Iraq and Iran: Playing the Balance, 1984-1989
          - Korea, 1985-1988
          - Last of the Superpower Summits: Making the Most of It, 1988 (Box 66)
          - Leaks and Lie Detectors
          - Letting the Foreign Service Serve: A Success in Chile, 1985-1990
          - Middle East Peace Process, Winter 1982-1983
          - Middle East Peace Process, September 1, 1982 through 1985
          - Miscellany
          - My Early Life
          - Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO) Meets the Conditions, 1988
          - Pocket History of the "Peace Process"
          - Polecat
          - Polecat: After the Revelation
          - Press
          - Reagan and Noriega
          - Reflections
          - Representation: A Lesson From My Time With President Nixon
          - Rudder: Fadlallah and the Hostages, 1986-1988 (Box 67)
          - Rudder
          - Shultz-Gates Meeting After Gates Became Acting Director of Central Intelligence, 1987
          - Signs of a Sea Change: Central America - Weaving a New Web
          - Signs of a Sea Change: Middle East Peace Process
          - Signs of a Sea Change: Reflagging, 1987
          - Soviet Union, October 1, 1984-April 1, 1985
          - Soviet Union, April 1, 1985-November 30, 1985
          - Soviet Union, Winter 1985-1986, arms to Iran, lie detector controversy, and PEN
          - Soviet Union, 1986
          - Soviet Union After Reykjavik, 1986-1987
          - Soviet Union, 1987
          - Soviet Union, 1987: The Cold War Is Over
          - Things Fall Apart, 1988
          - Tiresome, Troublesome, and Trivial: A Washington Interlude with Jim Wright and Henry Kissinger on Central America, 1987
          - U.S./Soviet Union, 1987
          - Wounded White House 1987: The Iran-Contra Controversy
      - Draft for Seoul Peace Prize acceptance speech, 1992
  - Subject file (Box 68)
    - Campbell, Tom
      - Correspondence
      - Notes
      - Schedule
    - Central America.
      Manuscript, author unknown
    - Central America. (Box 69)
      Manuscript
    - Clinton, Bill.
      Correspondence, printed matter
    - Economic conditions.
    - Gandhi, Rajiv.
      Memoranda, correspondence
    - Government documents as personal property.
      Correspondence, manuscript, printed matter
    - Greek Studies – Herodotus.
    - Hoover Institution.
      See Taiwan
    - Iran-Contra Affair
      - General.
      - Independent Counsel.
        Notes
    - "Israeli Politics and Foreign Policy" by Samuel J. Roberts.
    - Kuwait. "Free Kuwait" pin and stickers
    - Miscellany (Box 70)
    - Philosophy.
    - Sofaer, Abraham.
      Resume, memorandum, speech
    - Stanford, 1989.
    - Stanford Continuing Studies Program.
      Correspondence, syllabus, printed matter
    - Taiwan and the Hoover Institution.
      Correspondence, notes, printed matter, reports
    - United Nations.
      Remarks, reports, printed matter
    - United States. List of books in the Secretary of State's Library.
      Includes a computer disk
    - Vietnam.
      Outline by Charles Hill
  - Department of State file, 1968-1982 (Box 73)
    - Speeches and writings, primarily drafts of writings for Henry Kissinger
    - Notebooks (Box 75)
      - July 1978-May 12, 1981
      - May 14, 1981-August 7, 1982 (Box 76)
    - Subject file (Box 74)
      - Bruce, David K. E. White House statement on his death
      - Bunker, Ellsworth. Remarks, October 16, 1974
      - China.
        Typescript, reading list, printed matter
      - Davies, John Paton.
      - Foreign service.
        Correspondence, memoranda, notes, printed matter
      - Imperialism.
      - Kim Yun Tek.
        Chronology
      - Kissinger, Henry.
        Program, printed matter
      - Miscellany
      - Press.
      - Speech making.
      - Television news.
      - Vietnam.
  - Stanford Years file. Speeches and writings by Charles Hill (Box 76)
    - Notebooks, January 13, 1989 - July 15, 1992
    - Diaries, 1989-1991 (Box 77)
    - Drafts for Turmoil and Triumph (Box 79)
  - Political Officer in Hong Kong file, 1966-1969. (Box 84)
    Newsbriefs from the Japanese press in Peking (Beijing), China
    - 1966
      - October 17, 20, October 30
      - November 9-10
      - December 12-13, December 15-16, December 19, 24, December 26-29
    - 1967
      - January 5-20
      - February 3, 8, February 16-24, February 27-28
      - March 1, March 6-7, March 11-13, March 15-18, March 22, March 25-28, March 30
      - April 1-2, April 4-7, April 9-27, April 29-30
      - May 1, May 5-10, May 14-21, May 23, May 25-26, May 29
      - June 1-2, June 7-8, June 10-13, June 16, 23
      - July 3, 29
      - August 4, August 7-8, August 11, 16, August 28, 30
      - September 1-3, September 5
  - United Nations file, 1992-1996 (Box 71)
    - Article in Orbis, Summer 1993, entitled "An Agenda for Peace"
    - Letter to editor, New York Review of Books, July 1993
    - Printed matter
    - Speeches and writings (mostly notes)
    - U.N. and non-U.N. materials, including correspondence, notes, printed matter (Box 72)
  - Audio-visual file (Box 78)
    - Phonotapes
      - Panel on Political Culture in the Soviet Union
      - Charles Hill on KZSU, "Why the U.S. Policy in the Gulf Is Right,", January 23, 1991
      - National Press Club, with Boutros Boutros-Ghali
      - Institute for Historical Study talk, October 17, 1990
      - Charles Hill speaking on "Statecraft,", August 8, 1989
      - Max Kampelman, speech at Glassboro State College, New Jersey, February 24, 1992
    - Videotapes
      - Institute for International Studies (IIS), Advisory Council meeting, January 24-25, 1991
        (7 tapes)
      - Charles Hill on Viewer Call-in Program, C-Span, January 29, 1991
  - Stanford Years file (Box 85)
    - Subject file
      - Africa
        - "Horn of Africa: A History of Conflict" by Ryan Fortson
        - Article on Sudan
        - Article on Sudan from an Encyclopedia
        - Excerpt from book on Abyssinia
        - Article on Ethiopia, "A New Chance for a Fractured Land"
        - Excerpt from Ethiopia Under Mussolini by Alberto Sbacchi
        - "Nation Building in Black Africa," The World and I, March 1992
        - Ad for The Horn of Africa: From War to Peace by Paul Henze
        - Charles Hill notes
        - "War on the Nile: Winston Churchill and the Reconquest of the Sudan," Political Science Reviewer, undated
        - "Sudan's Turabi Predicts a Region-Wide Islamic 'Quake'," Mideast Mirror, January 9, 1992
        - Printed matter
      - Agricultural policy. Correspondence from Carol Brookins, World Perspectives, Inc., 1990
      - Alliances. Excerpt from Origins of Alliances by Stephen Walt
      - America
        - Charles Hill notes
        - Articles from PS: Political Science & Politics, December 1991
        - Printed matter
      - Argentina
        - Excerpt from Jorge Luis Borges, Selected Poems, 1923-1967
        - "Argentina: Living With Cruelty" by V.S. Naipaul, New York Review of Books, January 30, 1992
        - Printed matter
      - Arms control
        - Excerpt from anti-ballistic missile treaty
        - "What the ABM Treaty Means," Time, March 23, 1987
        - "Peace and National Security," speech by President Ronald Reagan, March 23, 1983
      - Asian nations
        - Charles Hill notes
        - Printed matter
      - Ballistic missiles
        - "Third World Ballistic Missiles," Scientific American, August 1990
        - Memo and reports from the Stanford Center for International Security and Arms Control, June 1990
      - Central Intelligence Agency. Charles Hill notes
      - China
        - "Titan Stirs," Economist, November 28, 1992
        - Charles Hill notes
        - Speech by Boutros Boutros-Ghali, December 14, 1994
        - "Old Man's New China" by P. Link, New York Review of Books, June 9, 1994
        - Chapter from Ideas Across Cultures by Paul Cohen and Merle Goldman
        - Printed matter
      - Civilization.
      - Clausewitz, Carl von. Paper by Peter Paret
      - Democracy
        - "From Authoritarianism to Democracy via Socioeconomic Development" (draft) by Robert Dahl, June 1994
        - Charles Hill notes
        - "Modes of Transition and Types of Democracy in Latin America, Southern & Eastern Europe" (draft) by T. Karl and P. Schmitter
        - Printed matter
        - "Social Requisites of Democracy Revisited" by Seymour Martin Lipset, address to the American Sociological Association, 1993
        - "Prospect Before Us: A World Rich, Democratic and (Perhaps) Peaceful" by H. S. Rowen, June 7, 1993 (Box 86)
        - "'We Hold These Truths': Strategies of Control in the Literature of the Founders" by Robert Ferguson
        - "Origins of American Constitutionalism" by Donald Lutz
        - "Democratization and International Security" by Francis Fukuyama
        - "Role of Electoral Politics in American Foreign Policy Formulation" by William Widenor
        - Printed matter
        - Charles Hill notes
        - "John Dewey on Democracy: The Task Before Us" by Richard Bernstein
      - Diplomacy
        - Notes and printed matter on George Kennan
        - "Golden Sunshine" by John Dewey, Virginia Quarterly Review, undated
        - "New Diplomacy: A Changing Process" by Elmer Plischke, Virginia Quarterly Review, Summer 1973
        - "Foreign Policy-Makers: Weakest Link?" by Charles Maechling, Jr., Virginia Quarterly Review, Winter 1976
        - "Tragedy of American Diplomacy: Twenty-Five Years Later" by Bradford Perkins
        - Letter to George Shultz from Sidney Drell, June 7, 1994
        - Printed matter
        - Diplomats in Residence, Hoover Institution
      - Diversity. Outline "A Contrapuntal Civilization,", September 26, 1991
      - Economics
        - "Modern Adam Smith," Economist, July 14, 1990
        - "From Geopolitics to Geo-Economics" by Edward Luttwak, National Interest, Summer 1990
        - "Two Paths to Prosperity" (Taiwan and South Korea), Economist, July 14, 1990
        - "What Everyone 'Knows' About Reaganomics" by Paul Roberts, Commentary, February 1991
        - "Law & Economics" by Theodore Roth, University of Chicago Magazine, August 1991
        - "New Wealth of Nations," Chapter 8 of Statecraft manuscript
        - Printed matter
      - Europe
        - "A New Money for Europe" by Graeme Littler and Jeffrey Tucker, World and I, November 1990
        - "European Revolution," Economist, November 9, 1991
        - "Excerpts from the Charter of Paris for a New Europe as Signed Yesterday," New York Times, November 21, 1990
        - "European Community," Economist, July 7, 1990
      - Fang Lizhi. "Diplomatic Asylum and Fang Lizhi" by Alfred Rubin, Diplomacy and Statecraft, 1990
      - Foreign relations
        - "Something Old, Something New: John Lewis Gaddis's 'New Conceptual Approaches'" by Thomas McCormick, Diplomatic History, undated
        - "Foreign Affairs as Domestic Affairs" by Akira Iriye, review of American Style of Foreign Policy: Cultural Politics and Foreign Affairs by Robert Dahl, Reviews in American History, March 1984
        - "'Culture' of the Arab-Israeli Relationship: An International Conflict in Its Psychological and Symbolic Dimensions," proposal by Stanford professors, 1990
        - "An Historic Challenge to Rethink How Nations Relate" by Harold Saunders, chapter from Psychodynamics of International Relationships
        - Notes from talk on "Barriers to the Negotiated Resolution of Conflict"